MATEUS M. FURQUIM MENDONÇA

Machine Learning and Software Engineer

@mfurquimdev@gmail.com

git mfurquimdev

in/mfurquimdev

@mfurquim.dev

Brazil

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Highly skilled software engineer with over 9 years of experience and a diverse background. Committed to team growth and innovation through effective mentoring and collaboration. Strong problem-solving skills with a passion for delivering high-quality software solutions.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Back-end Developer

📋 Jan 2021 - Present

DevGrid

United Kingdom (Remote)

Managed several microservices that employ machine learning algorithms to estimate house appliances' energy consumption.

- > Achieved up to 59% improvement in **Python** write operations on **Cassandra** through the safe utilization of unlogged batches.
- > Iteratively improved domain models following **Domain Driven Design** approach, increasing efficiency in delivering new features.

Embedded Software Developer

Autotrac

Nov 2019 - Aug 2020

Brasilia, DF - Brazil

Maintained security and logistic features of an embedded system for a customized hardware and Linux kernel.

- > Employed dependency injection and other SOLID principles to enhance C++ code quality and maintainability.
- > Implemented monitoring solutions to gather real-time performance data, ensuring optimal system efficiency and responsiveness.

DevOps Consultant

IBM

📋 Jan 2019 - Nov 2019

Prasilia, DF - Brazil

Collaborated with multiple teams to improve observability of the back-end services of a prominent banking institution.

- > Contributed to self-discovering services feature using etcd key-value store, consistent hashing and a federation of Prometheus.
- > Employed PromQL to develop alerts that detected low performance of new deployments and potential DDoS attacks.

INTERN EXPERIENCE

Security Software Researcher

LADES at UnB

Pasilia, DF - Brazil

Enhanced an Intrusion Detection System with unsupervised machine learning to strengthen the security measures of the Brazilian Army.

- > Configured a **Debian** server to capture all network packets in promiscuous mode using **Wireshark** and replay them in a controlled environment.
- > Successfully detected masked malicious network packets using K-Means clustering algorithm and distributed processing with Spark and Hadoop.

EDUCATION

Machine Learning DevOps Engineer

Udacity

Online

📋 Nov 2021 – Dez 2022

BEng. Software Engineering

Universidade de Brasilia (UnB)

🤋 Brasilia, DF - Brazil 👚 Mar 2011 – Jul 2017

University of Victoria (UVic)

Victoria, BC - Canada 📋 Jan 2014 – Apr 2015

LANGUAGES

PortugueseEnglish	Mother Tongue Fluent
Python	Working Knowledge
C/C++	Working Knowledge
Go	Intermediate Knowledge
Rust	Basic Knowledge